In this video we are going to discuss about second requirement of overlapping kernel execution with memory transferring
which is the asynchronous memory transferring. Here,
we have the program I showed you to visualize the common CUDA program execution steps in the previous video.
In this implementation,
memory copies are synchronize operations.
They block the host execution. To overlap memory transferring with kernel execution,
we need to perform this memory transferring asynchronously. For that
we are going to use cudaMemCpyAsync function. CudaMemCpyAsync function is almost similar to cudaMemCpy function.
But we can provide which stream this memory operation is going to execute as an argument to
this function as well. To perform a memory operation asynchronously CUDA runtime need the guarantee
that operating system will not move the virtual memory belongs to the memory being copied in the middle of the
memory transfer operation.
So we have to use pinned memory with this function call.
If we use unpinned memory, then this memory transfer will be a synchronous one which block the host execution.
Ok, let's use this function call to perform
asynchronous memory transferring operation now. In this example we are going to perform memory transferring
between host and device asynchronously.
Here, our kernel is similar to one we had in the previous common CUDA program step demonstration example,
and it just perform computations on the data transfer to the device.
So let's focus on the main function. Here,
We how to first add host pointers to hold memory for input and output of the GPU calculations.
Then we have to allocate pinned host memory for these pointers.
So to allocate pinned memory, we can use cudaMallocHost function
Now we need to create new CUDA stream.
So here, we have declared cuda stream type variable, and then we can use cudaStreamCreate function
to create a new stream. Then we can perform asynchronous memory transferring using cudaMemCpyAsync function
with this new stream.
Remember we have to provide our stream as the last argument for cudaMemCpyAsync function.
Now we can launch our kernel.
But remember here to provide news stream as the fourth kernel launch parameter as well.
But here, we are not going to use any shared memory so set the third kernel launch parameter to 0
and 4th one to new stream.
.
Ok, now we have to make our memory transferring device to host asynchronous as well.
So we can use cudaMemCpyAsync function
instead of cudaMemCpy function
here as well.
And finally we can call cudaStreamSynchronize on this stream to wait until all the functions in the
stream to execute.
Now let's look at what this program execution looked like.
In the nvvp.
So let me compile this program first and run it with nvvp command.
Ok, this is our output.
Now let me open up the output timeline for common cuda program execution steps program as well.
Now as you can see both of these outcomes are very similar. In new stream also
all the operations performed sequentially  as they should. Remember in this program,
all these cuda operations are asynchronous relative to the host.
But if we take one stream, operations put to that stream is going to execute in order.
So here even though all operations are asynchronous,
but in the device, all these cuda operations are going to execute in order.
Now here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to perform same set of operations we perform using stream one in an other stream as well.
Usually when we are using multiple streams, we are partitioned same host memory and transfer blocks of memory
to device using different streams.
But here to keep this example simple, I'm going to have separate memory pointer for new kernel launch.
Then I have to allocate memory for that kernel launch using cudaMallochost function as well.
Now we need another stream here.
So let me add another stream variable, and create that stream using cudaStreamCreate function.
Then we can perform same set of operations using new stream as well.
So let me transfer memory from device to host asynchronously first, and then we can launch our kernel in
this new stream.
After that we can copy the results of that kernel launch back to host asynchronously as well.
Now let me run this program again with nvvp.
Ok,
As you can see from this output there are multiple overlaps happen in this program execution.
Here, two kernel executions are overlapped. Kernel execution and memory transfer from host to device
from two streams are overlapped as well. But none of the memory transfers in the same direction have overlapped.
This is due to having only one PCI-e bus.
So the connection allows only one memory transfers in one direction. Two memory transfers allowed if the
direction of those memory transfers are different.
Remember if we use synchronize memory copy here then all these operations will be execute one after another
which will resulted in extended execution time.
But here with asynchronous memory transferring, we can overlapped memory transferring with kernel executions
and memory transfer to different direction. So in this way by overlapping these operations we can reduce
the execution time of our cuda program.