In this video i am going to show you how to create CUDA stream and how to perform asynchronous operations in a CUDA streams.
Let me first introduce you to tool called nvvp or
nvidia visual profiler which we are going to used to visualize our CUDA program execution.
Here we have a program which performs simple calculation on input data and store the results in output in
the device.
Here we have our kernel. It perform simple arithmatic operation on the input data.
Since we are going to visualize the execution of this progam with nvidia visual profiler, to have a clear output
i have introduce few iterations in the kernel as well.
Sole purpose of this for loop is to increase the execution time so we can clearly observe
the execution in nvvp or nvidia visual profiler. That's all. And in the main file i have perform usual stuff
.
you seen so far. I have initialzied input host array and transfer that data to the device and then launch the kernel
and wait for results to return and copy the results back to the host again. All these CUDA operations
are happening via default or null stream.
Now let's look at how this program execution is look like in the nvvp.
We can use nvvp to profile our kernels and have a visual output on how our kernels are going to execute
in a particular device.
We will learn more on nvvp tool in upcomming CUDA tool section
But here, we are going to just use this tool to visualize cuda program execution. So compile this program
and then type nvvp command and executable file name. Then our program will be open up in nvvp.
Initially you will be greeted with window like this.
Just click next and finish.
In this time line you can see when each CUDA operation is happen.
Now depending on the time consumed by your kernel and data transfers you might not see the kernel
execution properly. In such cases
you can expand time line until you can see the results clearly by holding control key and using mouse scroll.
.
Here you can see the order of your program. We perform host to device memory transfer first, then we have our kernel
execution,
and finally we transfered the results of kernel execution back to the host.
Notice in this window ,to the left, you can see a tree hierarchy which specify the memory copies, kernel executions
and which stream particular operation perform using these subtrees. Here all the operations we perform
here happen in the default stream or null stream and it had been notice in this subtree as well.
Ok,
Now you know how our usual progam look like in a nvvp time line.
Here's what I'm going to do next.
Our ultimate goal is to overlap kernel execution with memory transferring to reduce overall kernel execution time.
For that we need two things. We should be able to launch multiple kernels and we should be able to transfer
memory between host and device asynchronously.
So let's first look at how to perform multiple kernel launches.
As you may already aware, you can simply lauch multiple kernels by simply having that statement in the
host code.
But this is not what we are after. Launching multiple kernels in to the same stream does not help us  to make
kernel execution parallel since with in a single stream
CUDA operations follows strick ordering.
So if you launch same kernel multiple times using default stream
which means if you launch multiple kernels without specifying which steam to use explicitly, then those kernel launches
are going to excute one after another in the device.
So let's verify this fact first.
Ok, in this example I have kernel called simple kernel which prints hello from kernel to the console. In the main function
I am going to launch this kernel multiple times with one thread executing each. Now from the host perspective,
all three kernels launches we have here are asynchronous calls, so that hosts execution does not block
by these kernel launch statements.
So by looking at host perspective, someone may see all three kernels
runs parallel in the device. But since we use default stream for each of these kernel launches, these kernel launches
will be executed one after another.
Let's verify this fact with nvvp now.
So let me compile this program first.
And then run it with nvvp tool.
Ok, as you can see from the output all three kernels executes one after another in the default stream.
Which stream perticular kernel executes can be viewed by sub tree in the left side.
Here it says default, since all three kernels execute in the default stream.
If we have multiple streams, there will be multiple streams shown in this subtree.
So here we verify that multiple kernel launches to the same stream does not execute parallel in the device.
So how to perform multiple kernel launches with different stream then.
For that we have to first create necessary amount of streams first.
So let's see how to create new CUDA streams now. We can create new stream using cudaStreamCreate() function.
You have to provide pointer to a stream variable as the argument to this function. After creating
you can perform operations on this stream. You can delete stream by using cudaStreamDestroy function.
You have to provide the pointer to the stream you want to delete as the argument for this function.
If is still pending work in the stream when cudaStreamDestroy is called on that stream,  cudaStreamDestroy
returns immediately and resource associated with those streams are released automatically when
all the work is the stream has completed.
No we are going to perform asynchronous operations using these new streams.
So you need a way to check whether the operation in the stream finished or not.
You can use cudaStreamSynchronize function for that. cudaStreamSynchronize function call is a blocking
function call.
So this will hold host code execution until all the operations in the called stream are finished.
Also you can use cudaStreamQuery function as well. This function call check whether all the operations in the stream
completed, but does not block the host if they have not completed. CUDA stream query returns cudaSucess
if all the operations are complete or flag called cudaErrorNotReady if one or more operation is is still
executing or pending execution.
Ok, now let me launch kernel's in our previous example to
different streams. Here,
First we have to check whether our device have the parallel kernel execution capability or not.
Only the device with compute capability 2.0 or later
have this concurrent kernel execution capability.
You can check that with concurrent_kernels device property.
So let me query the device properties with
cudaGetDeviceProperties function call here.
Then we can use concurrent_kernel property to check whether our device allows concurrent kernel execution.
And if our device does not support concurrent kernel execution, then kernel launches we are going to
make here will be serialized.
We have three kernels here and we are going to launch those kernels to different streams.
So we need three streams.
Okay let me declare those streams first.
No we need to create those streams with cudaStreamCreate function.
We can specify which stream where particular kernel is going to execute by setting 4th kernel
launch parameter.
Since we are not considering about shared memory here, we can set 3rd kernel launch parameter to zero
and set 4th parameter to stream we want. Then we have to reclaim the resources associated with
this streams after our kernel execution finish.
So here we have to call cudaStreamDestroy function for each of our declared stream now.
Then here, we have cudaDeviceSynchronize function which will block the host thread until all the operations in
all the streams are finished.
Or we could cudaStreanSynchronize function here as well.
But since we have to wait until all the streams are finished,
let's not change this function call.
Now let me compiler this program and run it with nvvp.
The nvvp time line for this execution is looking like this.
Here you can see all three kernels have executed parallel. To highlight multiple kernel execution
Click the button with S letter at the top of the window.
This will make the execution happen in different streams to have different colors in the timeline.
So now you can identify the parallel execution of each kernel clearly.
Ok, now we know how to execute concurrent kernels in our device using multiple streams.
Now we have to find a way to transfer memory between host and device  asynchronously. In the next vedio
We are going to learn that as well.