In this video, we are going to implement summation of two arrays with cuda asynchronous functions and then
we will look at the performance gain we achieved from overlapping kernel executions and memory transferring.
Execution order of operations of our previous sum array implementation, would look like. Due to the blocking nature of
cudaMemCpy function call and use of cudaDeviceSynchronize function, arrange memory transfer operation
and kernel execution in a sequential line.
With CUDA non null streams and asynchronous function calls,
this is what we expect to achieve.
We are going to divide the input array in to predetermined number of data chunks and then we are going to execute
sum array kernel in different streams with one data chunk in each. Ok, let's jump in to the implementation.
Here, I have our previous implementation of sum array program. All we do is initializing two input arrays
and pass those to device,
and then we launch sum array kernel and after kernel execution finish, we transfer the results back to the
host and that's it. Now
I'm going to change this kernel implementation to launch multiple kernels and memory transfers to be in
different streams and to be asynchronous.
So let's set number of streams
we are going to use here, as the first thing in the main function here.
I'm going to use 8 steam,
so let's set that. Since we are going to execute summation for only part of the array in single stream
we have to set the number of elements are going to processed by each stream and number of bytes required to
hold that amount of elements as well.
So let's set those variables here as well.
To call asynchronous memory copy function, we have to provide pinned memory.
So I have to change this memory allocation with malloc function to memory allocations with
cudaMallocHost functions.
Now we have array initialization and sum array function call in CPU,
We are not going to change that,
so keep these line as they are. Then we can crate a new streams we are going to use here. Since
we are going to have multiple streams
we commonly store all these streams in a stream array.
Then we can iterate through these arrays while calling cudaStreamCreate function to create cuda
stream as each element in the stream array.
Ok, now we are going to transfer memory and launch sum array kernel in each stream.
So let's first set, block and grid size variables here. Notice grid size is now divided by factor of
number of streams as well.
Then we are going to iterate number of the stream amount of time while performing asynchronous memory transferring and
kernel launches with one stream per iteration.
Remember here, we have two input arrays, and we have to calculate offset of elements each stream
is going to process.
So here, first we have to calculate the element offset for input arrays. Now we can transfer
i'th data chunck from both input arrays asynchronously using i'th stream in the stream array.
.
Then we are going to launch our sum array kernel using i'th stream and we have to provide i'th data chunck
from each of these arrays as the input parameters.
And finally we can transfer the results back to host asynchronously as well.
Notice each of these operations are asynchronous. Which means these operation does not block host execution,
So all the kernel launches are happen to each stream almost at the same time.
After that we can again iterate through steam array and call cudaSteamDestroy function for each of these streams as well.
Then we have cudaDeviceSynchronize function call to wait until all the operations are finished.
Ok, let's look at what happen here with nvvp tool.
So let me compile this program with nvcc. And run the executable with nvvp.
Ok,
here we have the output for our program execution.
Here you can see that we have 8 streams.
And also notice that for each streams memory transfers made to host to device is overlap with kernel executions
and memory transfers made to device to host from different streams.
Also for any given time memory transferring for one direction is happen only from one stream. Two streams
can transfer data simultaneously for different direction, but not in the same direction.
In this way we can overlap our kernel execution with memory transfers to minimize overall program
execution.