In this video, we are going to discuss about blocking and non blocking streams
relative to the null stream, and explicit and implicit synchronization of a CUDA program.
Even though operations of a non-null streams like asynchronous memory transfers and kernel launches are
non-blocking with respect to host, these operations can block operations in the null stream. Also operation in the
null-stream can block operations in non-null stream as well.
Based on the blocking nature relative to the null-stream, non null streams are categorized in to two types.
Blocking streams and non-blocking streams.
If a non-null stream is a blocking stream, then null stream can block operation in it. Meaning the execution
of operations in those streams can be block waiting for earlier operations in the null-stream to complete.
If a non-null stream is a non-blocking stream,
It will not block on operations in the null stream.
The null stream is an implicit stream, which synchronize with all other blocking stream in the same
CUDA context.
In general when an operation is issued to null stream, the CUDA context wait on all operations previously
issued but all blocking streams, before starting that operation. Also any operation issued to
blocking streams
will wait on proceeding operation in the null stream to complete before executing. Streams created
using cudaStreamCreate function are blocking streams. Let me quickly show you the blocking nature of
streams, relative to the null stream created using cudaStreamCreate function.
In this example I'm going to launch one kernel using three non-null streams.
So here I created three streams with cudaStreamCreate function and then launch our test kernels
the these three streams.
Let me compile this program and run it with nvvp. Ok,
here we have our nvvp time line, since we are executing same kernel in all three streams, all the bars have
same color here,
We can change the color for each stream using a S mark in the top panel.
Ok now you can see the each stream in different colors. As you can see all three kernels have executed
parallel in our device.
Now let me go back to our code. Notice here,
we are using cudaStreamCreate to create our streams.
And as I mentioned in the presentation cudaStreamCreate function create blocking streams
relative to the null stream.
So let me demonstrate that fact here.
Here I am going to make our second kernel launch to be launch to the null stream.
We can simply do that by removing stream in the kernel launch parameters.
Ok,
Let me compile this program again, and run it with nvvp. The output timeline is like this now. Notice here
even though we have two non-null streams with two kernel launches which are asynchronous in the host perspective
still in the device, all these kernels execute one after another.
This is due to the blocking relationship null stream have with non-null streams. Stream one and stream three
created using cudaStreamCreate function,
So those streams are blocking streams
So the second kernel launch to the null stream has to wait until first kernel launch finished its execution in the
stream one. And in the third kernel launch to the stream three has to wait until kernel launch to null stream
to finish. Ok,
now we realize the blocking nature of null stream.
Now let me show you a way to get rid of this blocking nature.
The cuda runtime provides function call cudaStreamCreateWithFlags which allows customization of non null stream's
behaviors relative to the null stream.
Here, the flag argument determine the behavior of the created stream. Valid values for flag are
cudaSteramDefault, which is the default or blocking stream creation flag, cudaStreamNonBlocking, which is the
asynchronous or non-blocking stream creation flag. Specifying cudaSteamNonBlocking disable the blocking
behaviors of non-null stream, relative to the null steam.
Ok, let me modify our previous example to demonstrate the usage if this function.
Ok here,
I am going to make stream 3 as a non-blocking stream first. So here, instead of creating stream 3 with
cudaStreamCreate function, let's create it with using cudaStreamCreateWithFlag function,
and we are going to set flag to cudaStreamNonBlocking.
Now lets run this example again with nvvp.
In the output,
you can see that, two non null streams are execute parallel. This is because stream 3 is a non-blocking  steam,
,
so it does not have to wait until, kernel execution in null stream to finish.
Also null stream has to execute, its kernel only after stream 1 have finished the kernel execution in that stream
and this is because stream 1 is blocking stream, so null stream  has to wait until stream 1 finish
its execution.
Now let's make, both stream 1 and stream 3 to be non null streams.
So here, I have to create stream 1 using cudaStreamCreate with flag function as well.
Now let's see the nvvp timeline for this program execution.
So let me compile the program and run it with nvvp tool. Ok here,
we have the output,
you can see that all three streams have executed parallel. Notice here one stream is the null stream.
But since we make our non-null streams to non-blocking streams, non of the streams have to wait until kernel execution
is finished in other streams.
Even though we tend to have non blocking non null streams,
sometimes we have to make, non null streams blocking for synchronization purpose.
So, one advantage of blocking nature of null stream is that, null stream can be use as synchronization
mechanism between different streams.