In this video, we are going to quickly look at explicit and implicit synchronization in a cuda program.
Explicit synchronizations are pretty obvious.
The cuda runtime support several ways of explicitly synchronizing a cuda program at the grid level.
Synchronizing the device usign cudaDeviceSynchronize function, synchronizing a stream with cudaStreamSynchronize function,
synchronizing an event in a stream with cudaEventSynchronize function and synchronizing across streams
using an events. In case of cudaDeviceSynchronize function
all the operations in the device after this function call has to wait until all the operations in the device
which perform before function call to finish. In case of cudaStreamSynchronize funciton, operations
in the device, which comes after certain stream will be blocked. On the other hand implicit synchronization
happen as side effect of a blocking function calls. How ever the main purpose of those function calls are
not to introduce synchronize point in the device, but to perform some operations on the device like
memory transferring.
Implicit synchronization is a special interest in CUDA programming because runtime functions with implicit
synchronization behavior may cause un wanted blocking usually at the device level. Many memory related operations
imply blocking on all previous operations on the current device.
Remember here we are talking about device implicit synchronization not the host. But usually functions
we discuss here are also block the host execution as well.
Page lock memory allocation is one such operation. So pinned memory allocations using cudaMallocHost
function or zero copy memory allocation using cudaHostAlloc function
will block all the operations execution in the device until
memory allocation in the host to finish. Other operations like device memory allocation with cudaMalloc,
device memory set with cudaMemset, memory copies between two address on the same devices and modification to
L2 or shared memory configuration operations imply blockign of all previous operations on the curreant
device as well.