Ok, let's start our discussion on cuda events.
In this video we are going to learn about the basic usages of cuda events, how to declare and manage cuda events and
how to measure time between two cuda events as well.
An event in cuda is essentially a marker in a cuda stream associate with certain point in the flow of operations
in that stream.
Event can be used to synchronize multiple stream executions, monitor device progress and
measuring the execution time of any cuda operation as well.
The cuda API provides function that allows you to insert event at any point in a stream as well as query
for the event completion. An event recorded on a given stream will only be satisfied, that is complete,
when all the proceedings operation in that stream hove completed.  Also remember events is specified
on the default stream applied to all preceding operation in the all the cuda streams.
We will look at each of these usages in a minute. But let's first look at how to perform basic functionalities
associated with event. Basic functions use to mange cuda events are very much analogeous to the
functions we use to manage streams.
You can create cuda event by passing cuda event type pointer to the cudaEventCreate function.
Cuda event can be destroyed by cudaEventDestroy function. If the event has not yet been satisfied
when the cudaEventDestroy function is called,
the call returns immediately, and the resources associated with that event are released automatically
when the event is marked complete.
You can thing cuda event as an operation added to a cuda stream, whose only action when pop from the head of the
working queue, is to raise a host side flag to indicate the completion. An event is queue to
cuda stream usign cudaEventRecord function. The passed event can be used to either wait for or test for
the completion of all the proceedings operation in particular stream.
Waiting for an event blocks the
calling host thread and is performed using cudaEventSynchronize function.
You can test if an event has completed without blocking the host application using cudaEventQuery function.
And you  can measure the elapsed time of a cuda operation marked by two events using
cuda event elapsed time function.
Note cudaEventElapsedTime function returns the time elapsed between event start and stopped beign satisfied
in milliseconds and even start and stop
do not need to be associated with the same cuad stream.
Let me show you an example which highlight these functions and how we can use cuda events to measure
the execution time of a cuda operation.
Ok in this example I'm going to measure the execution time of a kernel.
Here we have the kernel we are going to measure the execution time.
Now let's complate the host code. Here i have
already defined size of a grid,
and block and grid variable. Now we have to create two events.
So here, let me add two cudaEvent type
variables called start and finished. Now we have to create these events.
For that we can use cudaEventCreate function with above declared variables.
Ok, here we need to measure the execution time of our kernel.
So here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to push one event, start event into the null stream before launching ourt kernel.
And then after launching the kernel I'm going to push end event. And then we can wait until end event to
pop from the work queue and measure the time between the start and end event.
So here, let me push the start event to the stream using cuda event record function.
Then we can launch our kernel in to the default stream. And then we can push end event to the default stream using
cudaEventRecord function again.
Now we have to wait until end event is execute in the stream.
So here, we have to use cudaEventSynchronize function with end event.
This function will block the host execution until end event reach in the stream.
Then we can measure the elapsed time between start time and end event using cudaElapsedTime function.
For this function,
We have to provide float to store the elapsed time in milliseconds and two events.
So let me declare a float type variable here.
No we can pass float variable, start event and end event as the argument in this way
to our cudaEventElapsedTime function. Then let's
printout the elapsed time here.
Finally we have to reclaim the memory allocated to cuda events
using cudaEventDestroy funciton.
Ok let me on this example now.
Ok, here you can see our program have printed out the execution time.
So far, we have measure the execution time by recording clock cycles before and after and operatio and
taking the difference between them.
You can add that timing mechanism here, and check whether the execution times we got from cudaEvent are same as the
execution time of that method.
If you do that you will realize the time acquired using
both the methods are pretty similar. And the error is always with in one milliseond range.