In this video we are going to look at configurable events in cuda and how to use those events to create
inter stream dependencies. In complex applications
It can be useful to introduce inter stream dependencies that block operations in one stream until the
operation in another streams have completed. Events can be used to add inter stream dependencies like that.
Before move on to inter stream dependencies, let me show you how to crate configurable event
in cuda.
You can use cudaEventCreateWithFlags function to create events with different set of properties and behaviours.
For this function,
We have to specify particular cuda event and specific flag related to the behavior we need.
So let's look at flags
We can use in this function. If the flag  is cudaEventDefault then the event will have default behavour.
The flag cudaEventBlockingSync specifies that synchronizing on this event with cudaEventSynchronize
funciton will block the calling thread. The default behaviour of cudaEventSynchronize is to spin
on the evnt using cpu cycles to constantly check the events status. With cudaEventBlockingSync flag set
the calling thread instead gives up the core it is running on to another thread or processed by
going to sleep untill the event is satisfied.
.
While this can leads to fewer wasted CPU cycles, if other useful work can be done, it can also lead to longer latencies
between events being satisfied and calling thread being activated. Passing event disable timing indicates
that the created event is only use for synchronization and does not need to record timing data.
Removing the overhead of taking time stamps will improve the performance of calls to
cudaStreamWaitEvent and cudaEventQuery functions.
The flag cudaEventInterprocess indicate that the created event may be used as a interprocess event.
Ok now let's move on to the
inter stream dependencies.
We can use cudaStreamWaitEvent function to create inter stream dependencies.
Ok, let me show you how to create a stream dependency with this function now.
Here we have a code similar to one we had in the demonstrate the blocking nature of the null stream.
Here we are launching same kernel in three non-null streams,
so if we compile this program and run the program with nvvp,
the outcome would look like this.
All the kernels in all streams executes paralelly.
Now let's introduce interstream dependency between stream one and three and see how the outcome would look like.
So here, i need a cuda event,
so let me declare that here, and then we can create the event with cudaCreateEventWithFlag function.
You can use
cudaEventCreate function as well.
But here, we do not wish to record timing for this event, therefore we can specify this option to cudaCreateEventWithFlag
function.
Then after launching K1 kernel, we can record this event and then we can use cudaStreamWaitEvent function
to make stream 3 to wait on this event.
This code line will guranteed that steam 3 operations which come after these statements
have to wait on this event to complete. After all these
we have to released the resources for our event with cudaEventDestroy function.
Ok, let's now run the program with nvvp.
So let me compile our program quickly, and then run the executable with nvvp. The outcome of nvvp
would look like this.
Here you can clearly see that kernels in stream 1 and stream 2 runs parallel, but stream 3 has to wait
to execute its kernel until the stream 1's event is triggered.
This is due to the inter stream dependency.
we introduce using cude event.