From this video onwards, we are going to start our discussion on CUDA streams.
So far, our sole purpose was to improve performance of a particular kernel based on CUDA programming
model, execution model and memory model.
But in this section we are going to discuss ways of improving overall program execution by dividing
workload among multiple kernels and executing those kernels concurrently on a device.
So far in this course, we followed strict model for launching a kernel. We first allocate and transfer data
to the device from the host and then we launch the kernel,
and after that we wait until the kernel execution finish using cudaDeviceSynchronize function,
and then we transfer the results back to the host.
This is the model we followed so far. Here we achieved the performance by executing one kernel parallel
on multiple data at the same time.
Parallelism we saw here normally refers to as the kernel level parallelism. Parallelism we are going
to discuss in this section is called grid level parallelism. In grid level parallelism
concurrency is achieved by launching multiple kernels to same device simultaneously and overlapping
memory transfers with kernel execution.
In our previous CUDA programmes, we transferred memory at the beginning of the program.
But as you may already  notice , device has limited amount of resources.
So it cannot operate on the all the data we pass simultaneously.
So what if we partition our data and transfer only partition enough to execute one kernel optimally
and while that kernel is executing on that partition we transfer another partition of data
and so on. In this way we can overlap kernel execution with memory transferring.
So overall execution time is going to reduce,
because of this operation overlapping as shown in this diagram. To achieve this type of overlapping
between operations we need a way to launch multiple kernels on the same device and we need a way to transfer
memory asynchronously.
This is where CUDA streams and asynchronous functions come to our rescue.
So let's first look  at what is a CUDA stream now. A stream is a sequence of command that execute in order.
So within a single stream operations follow strict ordering.
For example, if we put all the partition data chunks data kernels to one stream, then above mention
operation overlapping would not be possible. But different streams on the other hand may execute their command
without any kind of ordering with respect to other streams.
So the way to achieve above mention overlapping is to put memory operations and kernel launches for one data
partition in to a unique stream. We will discuss more in this in upcoming video.
Now,
let's look at CUDA asynchronous operations.
When we talk about synchronous or asynchronous behaviors of operation in CUDA we have to consider both
the host and device perspective.
Let's start the discussion from the host perspective. Function with synchronous behavior relative to the host
block the host thread until they complete. On the other hand functions with asynchronous behaviors
return control to the host immediately after being called. For example, in our previous implementations
memory copy function calls, memory set function calls and cudaDeviceSynchronize function calls were synchronous
function calls.
They block the host code execution. But kernel launches are asynchronous operations
so control was immediately return to the host after kernel launch instruction executed. Host does not has to wait until
kernel execution is finished in the device. Like I mention, synchronous and asynchronous behaviours depend on
whether you looking at function call from host point of view or device point of view.
Consider the kernel launch statement in this slide. Here I have launch 3 kernels in different streams
from the host.
Notice here, we launch second kernel using default stream or null stream. Now from the host point of view
all the kernel launches are asynchronous.
So host will not wait until any of these kernels are finish unless explicitly wait using synchronize function calls.
c
But from the device point of view, these kernel launches may or may not be executed in device at the same time depending on the
relationship stream 1 and stream 3 have
with the default stream.
So in this case even though these kernel launches are asynchronous relative to the host, but in the device
these kernel launches may or may not be asynchronous. In a upcoming video,
you will see reasoning behind this kind of behaviour as well.
Ok, let's now see what the null stream is. The null stream is the default stream that kernel launches and data transfers
use
if you do not explicitly specify the different stream. In all the examples we seen so far, we did perform CUDA
operations in the NULL stream.
Apart from all the things we done so far NULL stream has synchronization relationship with other asynchronous streams,
so null stream is commonly use as synchronization mechanism multiple streams
as you will see in the upcoming videos. Ok to wind of this video let me list some of the operations
which can be performed independently hence which can be overlapped or can perform concurrently using
different stream. Computations on the host, computations on the device, memory transfers from host to device,
memory transfers from the device to host, memory transfers within memory of a given device and
memory transfer among devices.
So in up coming videos you will see how to perform these operations concurrently using non-null streams.